I want to start by doing an experiment.
أودّ أن أبدأ بتجربة.
I'm going to play three videos of a rainy day.
سأقوم بعرض 3 فيديوهات ليوم ممطر.
But I've replaced the audio of one of the videos,
ولكنّي قمت بتبديل الصّوت لأحد الفيديوهات،
and instead of the sound of rain,
وبدلاً من صوت المطر،
I've added the sound of bacon frying.
قمت بإضافة صوت قلي اللحم المقدّد.
So I want you think carefully which one the clip with the bacon is.
لذا أريد منكم أن تفكروا مليًّا، أيّ فيديو يحوي صوت القلي.
(Rain falls)
(صوت المطر يتساقط)
All right.
حسناً.
Actually, I lied.
في الحقيقة، لقد كذبت.
They're all bacon.
جميعهم لهم صوت القلي.
(Bacon sizzles)
(صوت اللحم المقدد يُقلى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
My point here isn't really to make you hungry
هدفي هنا ليس جعلكم تشعرون بالجوع
every time you see a rainy scene,
في كلّ مرة تشاهدون فيها منظرًا ممطرًا،
We're not looking for accuracy.
فنحن لا نتحرّى الدّقة.
So on the subject of deception,
لذا، في موضوع الخداع،
I wanted to quote one of my favorite authors.
أردت أن أقتبس من أحد كتّابي المفضّلين.
In "The Decay of Lying," Oscar Wilde establishes the idea
في كتاب "عقد الكذب"، أسسّ (أوسكار وايلد) فكرة أنّ
that all bad art comes from copying nature and being realistic;
الفن الرديء يأتي من محاكاة الطّبيعة ومن الواقعيّة،
and all great art comes from lying and deceiving,
والفن العظيم يأتي من الكذب والخداع،
and telling beautiful, untrue things.
ومن قول الأشياء الجميلة الكاذبة.
So when you're watching a movie
لذا عندما تشاهد فيلمًا
and a phone rings,
ويرنّ هاتفٌ ما،
it's not actually ringing.
إنّه لا يرنّ حقيقةً.
It's been added later in postproduction in a studio.
تمّ إضافة الرّنين لاحقًا في مرحلة ما بعد الإنتاج، في الاستوديو.
All of the sounds you hear are fake.
كلّ الأصوات التي تسمعها مزيّفة.
Everything, apart from the dialogue,
كلّ شيء، عدا الحوار بين الأشخاص،
is fake.
هو مزيّف.
When you watch a movie and you see a bird flapping its wings --
عندما تشاهد فيلمًا وترى عصفورًا يرفرف بأجنحته --
(Wings flap)
(رفرفة أجنحة)
They haven't really recorded the bird.
لم يقوموا فعليًّا بتسجيل صوت العصفور.
It sounds a lot more realistic if you record a sheet
فالصوت يبدو حقيقيًّا أكثر إذا سجّلتَ صوتَ شرشف
or shaking kitchen gloves.
أو صوت احتكاك قفّازات المطبخ.
(Flaps)
(رفرفات)
The burning of a cigarette up close --
احتراق السّيجارة عن قرب--
(Cigarette burns)
(سيجارة تحترق)
It actually sounds a lot more authentic
في الواقع سيبدو واقعيًّا أكثر بكثير
if you take a small Saran Wrap ball
إن أخذت كرة صغيرة من ورق النّايلون المستخدم في التّغليف
and release it.
وقُمتَ بفردها.
(A Saran Warp ball being released)
(كرة من ورق النايلون يتم فردها)
Punches?
اللكمات؟
(Punch)
(لكمة)
Oops, let me play that again.
دعوني أعرض ذلك مجدّدًا.
That's often done by sticking a knife in vegetables,
عادةً يتمّ ذلك بغرز سكّين في الخضار،
usually cabbage.
ملفوف غالبًا.
(Cabbage stabbed with a knife)
(ملفوف يُطعن بسكين)
The next one -- it's breaking bones.
التالي هو صوت كسر العظام.
(Bones break)
(عظام تتكسّر)
Well, no one was really harmed.
حسناً، لم يتأذّى أحدٌ حقًّا.
It's actually ...
إنه في الواقع ...
breaking celery or frozen lettuce.
صوت كسر كرفس أو خس مجمد.
(Breaking frozen lettuce or celery)
(كسر خس مجمد أو كرفس)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
as a trip to the supermarket
كزيارة إلى المتجر
and going to the vegetable section.
والتوجّه إلى قسم الخضار.
But it's often a lot more complicated than that.
بل غالبًا ما يكون معقّدًا أكثر من ذلك.
So let's reverse-engineer together
لذا دعونا نهندس عكسيًّا معًا
the creation of a sound effect.
عمليّة إنشاء التّأثير الصوتي.
One of my favorite stories comes from Frank Serafine.
إحدى قصصي المفضّلة تأتي من (فرانك سيرافيني).
He's a contributor to our library,
إنّه أحد المساهمين في مكتبتنا الصوتيّة،
and a great sound designer for "Tron" and "Star Trek" and others.
ومصمّم صوت رائع لأفلام مثل "ترون" و"ستار تريك" وغيرها.
He was part of the Paramount team that won the Oscar for best sound
كان عضوًا في فريق شركة "باراماونت" وفاز بجائزة الأوسكار كأفضل مؤثّرات صوتيّة
for "The Hunt for Red October."
عن فيلم "الصّيد في أكتوبر الأحمر".
In this Cold War classic, in the '90s,
يتحدث الفيلم عن الحرب الباردة في التّسعينات،
they were asked to produce the sound of the propeller of the submarine.
وطُلب من الفريق إنتاج صوت مروحة الغوّاصة.
So they had a small problem:
واجهتهم مشكلة صغيرة:
they couldn't really find a submarine in West Hollywood.
لم يتمكّنوا من إيجاد غوّاصة في هوليوود الغربيّة.
So basically, what they did is,
وبالتّالي، ما فعلوه هو أنهم،
they went to a friend's swimming pool,
ذهبوا الى مسبح أحد أصدقائهم،
and Frank performed a cannonball, or bomba.
وقام (فرانك) بالغطس في المسبح.
They placed an underwater mic
قاموا بزرع لاقط صوت تحت الماء
and an overhead mic outside the swimming pool.
ولاقط صوت آخر خارج المسبح.
So here's what the underwater mic sounds like.
هكذا كان الصوت تحت الماء.
(Underwater plunge)
(صوت غطس)
Adding the overhead mic,
ومع إضافة صوت اللاقط الخارجي،
it sounded a bit like this:
بدا الصوت هكذا:
(Water splashes)
(صوت رشق الماء)
So now they took the sound and pitched it one octave down,
ثم قاموا بخفض تردد الصوت بمقدار أوكتاف واحد،
sort of like slowing down a record.
بدا الأمر كأنهم يبطئون التسجيل.
(Water splashes at lower octave)
(صوت الماء بتردد منخفض)
And then they removed a lot of the high frequencies.
ثم أزالوا الأصوات ذات التردد العالي.
(Water splashes)
(رشق ماء)
And pitched it down another octave.
وقاموا بتخقيض تردد الصوت مرة أخرى.
(Water splashes at lower octave)
(رشق ماء بتردد أخفض)
And then they added a little bit of the splash
ثم أضافوا صوت رشق الماء
from the overhead microphone.
من اللاقط الخارجي.
(Water splashes)
(صوت رشق ماء)
And by looping and repeating that sound,
وبتكرار الصوت النهائي عدّة مرّات،
they got this:
حصلوا على هذا الصوت:
(Propeller churns)
(صوت هدير مروحة)
So, creativity and technology put together in order to create the illusion
إذاً، بالإبداع والتقنيّات الحديثة تمكّنوا من إيهامنا
that we're inside the submarine.
أننا داخل غوّاصة.
But once you've created your sounds
لكن بعد أن تُنتج الأصوات
and you've synced them to the image,
وتُزامنها مع الصّور،
you want those sounds to live in the world of the story.
عليك أن تجعل هذه الأصوات جزءًا حيًّا من القصّة.
And one the best ways to do that is to add reverb.
وأحد أفضل الطّرق للقيام بذلك هي إضافة الصّدى.
So this is the first audio tool I want to talk about.
هذه أوّل طريقة أريد الحديث عنها.
Reverberation, or reverb, is the persistence of the sound
الصّدى هو استمرار وجود الصوت
after the original sound has ended.
بعد تلاشي الصّوت الأصلي.
So it's sort of like the --
إذاً هو عبارة عن --
all the reflections from the materials,
انعكاس الصّوت عن المواد،
the objects and the walls around the sound.
والأشياء والجدران الموجودة حول منبع الصّوت.
Take, for example, the sound of a gunshot.
لنأخذ مثلاً صوت الطلق الناري.
The original sound is less than half a second long.
الصّوت الأصلي مدته أقل من نصف ثانية.
(Gunshot)
(صوت طلق ناري)
By adding reverb,
وبإضافة الصدى،
we can make it sound like it was recorded inside a bathroom.
يمكننا جعله يبدو كأنه سُجّلَ في الحمّام.
(Gunshot reverbs in bathroom)
(صدى الطلق الناري في الحمّام)
Or like it was recorded inside a chapel or a church.
أو كأنّه سُجّل في كنيسة.
(Gunshot reverbs church)
(صدى الطلق الناري في الكنيسة)
Or in a canyon.
أو في وادٍ.
(Gunshot reverbs in canyon)
(صدى الطلق الناري في وادٍ)
So reverb gives us a lot of information
بالتالي، الصّدى يعطينا الكثير من المعلومات
about the space between the listener and the original sound source.
عن المسافة بين المستمع ومنبع الصوت الأصلي.
If the sound is the taste,
إذا كان الصّوت هو الطعم،
then reverb is sort of like the smell of the sound.
فإنّ الصّدى هو رائحة الصوت.
But reverb can do a lot more.
إلّا أنّ الصدى يفعل أكثر من ذلك.
Listening to a sound with a lot less reverberation
إنّ الإستماع إلى صوت بصدى أقل من
than the on-screen action
الحدث الذي على الشاشة
is going to immediately signify to us
سوف يُشعرنا فورًا
that we're listening to a commentator,
وكأننا نستمع إلى معلّق،
to an objective narrator that's not participating in the on-screen action.
أو إلى راوٍ ليس له علاقة بالأحداث الجارية على الشاشة.
Also, emotionally intimate moments in cinema
كذلك فإنّ اللحظات العاطفية في السينما
are often heard with zero reverb,
لا نستخدم فيها الصدى أبدًا،
because that's how it would sound if someone was speaking inside our ear.
لأننا نريد للصوت أن يبدو وكأنّ أحدهم يهمس في أذننا.
On the completely other side,
من جهة أخرى،
adding a lot of reverb to a voice
إضافة الكثير من الصدى
is going to make us think that we're listening to a flashback,
سيجعلنا نظن أننا نستمع إلى حدث في الماضي،
or perhaps that we're inside the head of a character
أو كأننا داخل رأس الشخص المتحدث
or that we're listening to the voice of God.
أو أننا نستمع إلى صوت الله.
Or, even more powerful in film,
أو إلى شخصية سينمائية قوية،
Morgan Freeman.
مثل (مورغان فريمان).
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So --
إذًا --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But what are some other tools or hacks
ما هي الحيل والأدوات الأخرى
that sound designers use?
التي يستخدمها مهندسو الصوت؟
Well, here's a really big one.
حسنًا، إليكم هذه الحيلة المهمّة
It's silence.
إنها الصمت.
A few moments of silence is going to make us pay attention.
بضعة ثوانٍ من الصمت ستجلعنا نوجّه اهتمامنا لما هو قادم
And in the Western world,
في العالم الغربي،
we're not really used to verbal silences.
لسنا معتادين على الصمت أثناء الحديث.
They're considered awkward or rude.
بل يُعتبر مريبًا وقحًا.
So silence preceding verbal communication
لذلك الصمت أثناء الحديث
can create a lot of tension.
يؤدّي إلى الكثير من التوتّر.
But imagine a really big Hollywood movie,
لكن تخيّلوا فيلمًا سينمائيًّا ضخمًا،
where it's full of explosions and automatic guns.
مليئًا بأصوات الانفجارات والأسلحة الرشّاشة.
Loud stops being loud anymore, after a while.
بعد مدة ستصبح الأصوات العالية شيئاَ عاديًّا.
So in a yin-yang way,
إذًا، وفق قانون (ين يانغ)،
silence needs loudness and loudness needs silence
الصمت يحتاج الضّجيج والضّجيج يحتاج الصمت
for either of them to have any effect.
ليكون لهما تأثيرٌ واضح.
But what does silence mean?
لكن، ماذا نعني بالصمت؟
Well, it depends how it's used in each film.
ذلك يعتمد على طريقة استخدامه في كلّ فيلم على حدى.
Silence can place us inside the head of a character
الصمت يُدخلنا إلى عقل الشخصية
or provoke thought.
أو يحرضنا على التفكير.
We often relate silences with ...
نحن نربط عادةً بين الصمت ...
contemplation,
والتأمّل،
meditation,
والتدبّر،
being deep in thought.
والتفكير بعمق.
But apart from having one meaning,
لكن بعيدًا عن المعنى الواحد للكلمة،
silence becomes a blank canvas
الصمت هو صفحة بيضاء
upon which the viewer is invited to the paint their own thoughts.
تدعو المشاهدين ليرسموا أفكارهم عليها.
But I want to make it clear: there is no such thing as silence.
لكنني أودّ أن أوضّح الصمت ليس له وجود.
And I know this sounds like the most pretentious TED Talk statement ever.
وأعلمُ أنّ ذلك يبدو كأكثر عبارة رنّانة في تاريخ محادثات TED.
But even if you were to enter a room with zero reverberation
فحتّى لو كنتَ في غرفة خالية من الصدى
and zero external sounds,
والأصوات الخارجية،
you would still be able to hear the pumping of your own blood.
فستسمع صوت الدّم يجري في عروقك.
And in cinema, traditionally, there was never a silent moment
وفي السينما، عادةً لا يوجد لحظات صمت
because of the sound of the projector.
لوجود صوت جهاز العرض.
And even in today's Dolby world,
واليوم، رغم وجود نظام (دولبي) لتقليل الضجيج،
there's not really any moment of silence if you listen around you.
ليس هناك أيّ لحظة صمت.
There's always some sort of noise.
دائمًا يوجد ضجيج من نوعٍ ما.
Now, since there's no such thing as silence,
الآن، بما أن الصمت ليس له وجود،
what do filmmakers and sound designers use?
ماذا يستخدم صُنّاع الأفلام ومهندسو الصوت؟
Well, as a synonym, they often use ambiences.
حسنًا، يستخدمون أصوات البيئة المحيطة.
Ambiences are the unique background sounds
وهي الأصوات الموجودة في الخلفية
that are specific to each location.
والتي تميّز كل مكان عن آخر.
Each location has a unique sound,
كلّ موقع له صوت يميّزه،
and each room has a unique sound,
وكلّ غرفة لها صوت يميّزها،
which is called room tone.
يسمّى نغمة الغرفة.
So here's a recording of a market in Morocco.
هذا صوت أحد أسواق المغرب.
(Voices, music)
(أصوات أشخاص وموسيقى)
And here's a recording of Times Square in New York.
وهذا صوت ساحة التايمز في نيويورك.
(Traffic sounds, car horns, voices)
(أصوات المرور، وأبواق السيارات)
Room tone is the addition of all the noises inside the room:
نغمة الغرفة هي جميع الأصوات الإضافية في الغرفة:
the ventilation, the heating, the fridge.
كجهاز التهوية، جهاز التدفئة، البرّاد.
Here's a recording of my apartment in Brooklyn.
هذا تسجيل لأصوات شقتي في (بروكلين).
(You can hear the ventilation, the boiler, the fridge and street traffic)
(أصوات التهوية، السخّان، البرّاد، ازدحام السيارات)
Ambiences work in a most primal way.
أصوات البيئة لها تأثير أساسي.
They can speak directly to our brain subconsciously.
فهي تتوجه مباشرة لأدمغتنا دون وعي منّا.
So, birds chirping outside your window may indicate normality,
إذًا، تغريد الطيور قرب نافذتك يُعتبر شيئًا عاديًّا،
perhaps because, as a species,
والسبب في ذلك أننا،
we've been used to that sound every morning for millions of years.
اعتدنا على ذلك الصوت كل صباح ولملايين السنين.
(Birds chirp)
(صوت تغريد طيور)
On the other hand, industrial sounds have been introduced to us
من جهة أخرى، الأصوات الاصطناعية تم تقديمها لنا
a little more recently.
منذ عهد قريب.
Even though I really like them personally --
ورغم حبي للأصوات الاصطناعية --
they've been used by one of my heroes, David Lynch,
التي استخدمها أحد أروع المخرجين "ديفيد لينش"،
and his sound designer, Alan Splet --
ومهندس الصوت "آلان سبلت" --
industrial sounds often carry negative connotations.
إلّا أنّها تحمل دلالات سلبيّة.
(Machine noises)
(صوت محرك)
Now, sound effects can tap into our emotional memory.
حاليًّا، المؤثرات الصوتية يمكنها البقاء في ذاكرتنا طويلًا.
Occasionally, they can be so significant
وعادةً ما تكون مميزة لدرجة
that they become a character in a movie.
أن تصبح بنفس أهميّة شخصيات الفيلم.
The sound of thunder may indicate divine intervention or anger.
صوت الرعد قد يشير إلى الغضب أو إلى تدخّل إلهي.
(Thunder)
(صوت رعد)
Church bells can remind us of the passing of time,
صوت أجراس الكنيسة يذكرنا بأنّ الوقت يمرّ،
or perhaps our own mortality.
أو ربما يذكرنا بالموت.
(Bells ring)
(صوت أجراس)
And breaking of glass can indicate the end of a relationship
وصوت تكسّر الزجاج قد يشير إلى نهاية علاقة عاطفية
or a friendship.
أو نهاية صداقة،
(Glass breaks)
(صوت تكسّر زجاج)
Scientists believe that dissonant sounds,
يؤمن العلماء أنّ الأصوات الناشزة،
for example, brass or wind instruments played very loud,
كأصوات الآلات النفخية أو النحاسية العالية،
may remind us of animal howls in nature
قد تذكّرنا بعواء الحيوانات البرّيّة
and therefore create a sense of irritation or fear.
وبالتالي سيمنحنا الإحساس بالخوف أو الانزعاج.
(Brass and wind instruments play)
(صوت آلات نحاسية و نفخية)
So now we've spoken about on-screen sounds.
حتى الآن، تحدثنا عن الأصوات التي تظهرعلى الشاشة.
But occasionally, the source of a sound cannot be seen.
لكن أحيانًا، مصدر الصوت لا يتم عرضه.
That's what we call offscreen sounds,
وهو ما يدعى " أصوات الخلفية "،
or "acousmatic."
أو "الأصوات مجهولة المصدر".
Acousmatic sounds --
الأصوات مجهولة المصدر--
well, the term "acousmatic" comes from Pythagoras in ancient Greece,
هو مصطلح وضعه "فيثاغورس" في اليونان،
who used to teach behind a veil or curtain for years,
حيث كان يقوم بتدريس طلابه من خلف الستارة لسنوات،
not revealing himself to his disciples.
دون أن يُظهر نفسه لهم.
I think the mathematician and philosopher thought that,
إنّ الفلاسفة وأساتذة الرياضيات اعتقدوا
in that way,
أنه بتلك الطريقة،
his students might focus more on the voice,
سيركز الطلاب أكثر على الصوت،
and his words and its meaning,
والكلمات والمعاني،
rather than the visual of him speaking.
بدلاً من التركيز على شكل الأستاذ وهو يتحدث.
So sort of like the Wizard of Oz,
بشكل مشابه لفيلم "ساحر بلدة أوز"،
or "1984's" Big Brother,
أو فيلم "الأخ الأكبر" من إنتاج عام 1984،
separating the voice from its source,
حيث تم فصل الصوت عن مصدره،
separating cause and effect
فصل التأثير الصوتي عن مُسبّبه
sort of creates a sense of ubiquity or panopticism,
و خلق الشعور بوجود الصوت في كل مكان،
and therefore, authority.
بالتالي التأثير بقوة على المشاهد.
There's a strong tradition of acousmatic sound.
الأصوات مجهولة المصدر تُعتبر من التقاليد الصارمة.
Nuns in monasteries in Rome and Venice used to sing in rooms
اعتادت راهبات الأديرة في روما والبندقيّة على الغناء وهنّ على ارتفاع
up in galleries close to the ceiling,
قريب من السقف،
creating the illusion that we're listening to angels up in the sky.
لكي نتخيل أننا نستمع إلى غناء الملائكة في السماء.
Richard Wagner famously created the hidden orchestra
(ريتشارد فاغنر) قام بتأسيس الأوركسترا المخفية الشهيرة
that was placed in a pit between the stage and the audience.
ووَضَعَها في مكان منخفض بين المسرح و الجمهور.
And one of my heroes, Aphex Twin, famously hid in dark corners of clubs.
و"أفيكس توين" الذي أعتبره من العظماء قام بإخفائها في زوايا المسرح المظلمة.
I think what all these masters knew is that by hiding the source,
أعتقد أن هؤلاء أدركوا أنهم بإخفاء مصدر الصوت،
you create a sense of mystery.
يخلقون جوًّا من الغموض.
This has been seen in cinema over and over,
ذلك كان ملحوظًا في السينما أكثر من مرة،
with Hitchcock, and Ridley Scott in "Alien."
مثلاً في فلم "الفضائيون" من إخراج هيتشكوك وريدلي سكوت.
Hearing a sound without knowing its source
سماع الصوت دون معرفة مصدره
is going to create some sort of tension.
سيجعل المشاهد يتوتّر.
Also, it can minimize certain visual restrictions that directors have
كما يقلل من القيود المفروضة على المخرجين من ناحية العرض
and can show something that wasn't there during filming.
فيستطيعون الإدعاء بوجود شيء ما لم يكن موجودًا أثناء التصوير.
And if all this sounds a little theoretical,
جميع هذه الأصوات عرضتها بشكل نظري،
I wanted to play a little video.
لذلك سأعرض مقطع فيديو صغير الآن.
(Toy squeaks)
(صوت دمية البطة)
(Typewriter)
(صوت كتابة على الحاسوب)
(Drums)
(صوت قرع طبول)
(Ping-pong)
(صوت كرة الطاولة)
(Knives being sharpened)
(سكاكين تحتك ببعضها)
(Record scratches)
(تشويش)
(Saw cuts)
(صوت منشار)
(Woman screams)
(صراخ إمرأة)
What I'm sort of trying to demonstrate with these tools
ما أحاول شرحه هنا
is that sound is a language.
هو أن الصوت عبارة عن لغة.
It can trick us by transporting us geographically;
يمكنها السفر بنا إلى أي مكان،
it can change the mood;
يمكنها تغيير مزاجنا،
it can set the pace;
يمكنها نشر الطمأنينة؛
it can make us laugh or it can make us scared.
يمكنها جعلنا نضحك بل ويمكنها إخافتنا.
On a personal level, I fell in love with that language
على الصعيد الشخصي وقعتُ في حب تلك اللغة
a few years ago,
منذ سنوات،
and somehow managed to make it into some sort of profession.
وبطريقة ما، تمكنت من تحويلها إلى مهنة.
And I think with our work through the sound library,
وأعتقد أننا بالعمل على المكتبة الصوتيّة،
we're trying to kind of expand the vocabulary of that language.
سنتمكن من إثراء وتوسيع مفردات هذه اللغة.
And in that way, we want to offer the right tools
لذلك، علينا تأمين الوسائل المناسبة
to sound designers,
لمهندسي الصوت،
filmmakers,
صانعي الأفلام،
and video game and app designers,
مصممي الألعاب والتطبيقات،
to keep telling even better stories
لكي نقدّم أعمالاً أفضل
and creating even more beautiful lies.
ونخلق المزيد من الكذبات الجميلة.
So thanks for listening.
شكرًا لإستماعكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)